A Finding Aid to the Solon H. Borglum and Borglum Family Papers, 1864-2002, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Solon H. Borglum and Borglum family papers
1864-2002
Archives of American Art
Borglum, Solon Hannibal, 1868-1922
AAA.borgsolo
Archival Resource Key
11.5 Linear feet
The Solon H. Borglum and Borglum family papers date from 1864 to 2002 and measure 11.5 linear feet. The collection documents Solon Borglum's personal life and his career as a sculptor specializing in Western themes through biographical material, family and general correspondence, writings and notes, research for his biography, financial and business letters, printed material, photographs and artwork.
Biographical Note
Solon Hannibal Borglum was born in Ogden, Utah in 1868. His father Jens (James) Borglum and wife Ida emigrated to America in 1864, as Mormon converts. James took a second wife Christina who was the mother of Solon and his older brother John Gutzon de la Mothe. Christina left the family after just a few years, when James left the Mormon Church. James and Ida raised the large family, which included Solon, Gutzon, Miller, Arnold, August, Anna, Harriet, Theodora and Frank. Solon spent most of his childhood in Fremont, Nebraska, and in 1893 he became a ranch hand in Southern California. At this time he also developed an interest in art which he shared with his brother Gutzon, who was studying painting in Los Angeles.
From 1885 to 1893 Solon ran a ranch on his father's land in central Nebraska, but also took painting lessons from artist J. Laurie Wallace. After spending a short time at his brother's studio in Sierra Madre, and living as an artist in Santa Ana, he studied at the Cincinnati Art Academy under Louis T. Rebisso from 1895 to 1897. Solon then went to Paris where he met sculptor Augustus Saint-Gaudens who persuaded him to study sculpture at the Academie Julian. He studied there under Denys Puech and won numerous awards for works exhibited both in France and the United States. In 1898 Solon married Emma Vignal in Paris. They spent four months at the Crow Creek Reservation in South Dakota, an experience that greatly influenced his work. In 1901 Solon was elected to the National Sculpture Society, later becoming its vice president, and set up a studio in New York. Despite his success, such as winning the gold medal at the Art Palace at the 1904 World's Fair, confusions began between him and his brother Gutzon who decided to also become a sculptor. In 1906 he moved with his wife and children, Paul and Monica, to a farm in Connecticut called "Rocky Ranch." Artist Paul Manship became his student helper and lived with the family. Solon received commissions to do many monuments and memorials, but also continued to exhibit his work and participate in the local Silvermine Group of Artists.
From 1916 to 1917 Solon taught at the Beaux-Arts Institute of Design in New York and also developed ideas for an art textbook called Sound Construction, which he worked on with his student assistant Mildred Archer Nash. In 1918, he enlisted in the YMCA for overseas war work, attached to the Third and Fifth French Army. While there he was also the Director of Sculpture at the specially organized American Expeditionary Forces Art Training Center. When he returned home, he decided to establish the School of American Sculpture in New York City. He ran the school with great success, and gave many lectures on art and his experiences overseas until his sudden death after an appendectomy in January of 1922. His legacy was carried on by his wife Emma until her death in 1934, at which point his daughter Monica and her husband, A. Mervyn Davies, oversaw the exhibition of his artwork, and in 1974 published his biography Solon H. Borglum: "A Man Who Stands Alone".
Scope and Contents
The Solon H. Borglum and Borglum family papers date from 1864 to 2002 and measure 11.5 linear feet. The collection documents Solon Borglum's personal life and his career as a sculptor specializing in Western themes through biographical material, family and general correspondence, writings and notes, research for his biography, financial and business letters, printed material, photographs and artwork.
Biographical material contains documents providing information on the Borglum Family history as well as Solon's military service and memorial. Also found is a leather portfolio of ephemera kept by Emma Borglum. Family correspondence includes numerous letters between Solon and Emma and various members of their extended family. The letters discuss family events, everyday life, Solon's military service, and family history. General Correspondence pertains to Solon's career as an artist and includes his incoming and outgoing correspondence with galleries, foundries, patrons, fellow artists such as Augustus Saint-Gaudens, and others. Later correspondence from galleries, museums, foundries, historical societies, and other individuals and organizations, is addressed to his daughter Monica Borglum and concerns Solon's artwork and legacy after his death. Writings and notes include material written by Solon Borglum and material written by others. Solon's writings include project proposals as well as essays, lectures, and other notes on the topics of his own works of art, art and form, and his participation in World War I. Also found are Solon's diary, notebooks, and address books kept during the last five years of his life. Writings by others include writings by Emma and others about Solon Borglum, as well as guest books for the Silvermine Group of Artists.
Series five contains documents compiled by Monica Borglum Davies and her husband A. Mervyn Davies for a biography Solon Borglum. Included are their research files and notes as well as heavily edited drafts of book sections and draft manuscripts and notes. Financial and business records document Solon's professional career and legacy, including project contracts and financial proposals, account books, ledgers, receipts, and items regarding the Solon H. Borglum Sculpture and Education Fund. Printed material contains items about Solon Borglum's career and artwork compiled by his daughter, Monica Davies, and includes exhibition catalogs, exhibition announcements, brochures, programs, clippings, reports, and other publications. Also included is the textbook Sound Construction.
This collection also contains numerous photographs, including Solon's personal and family photographs, and photographs of his artwork. Family and personal photographs consist of photos of Solon taken throughout his career, including his time in military service, photos of his family and friends, various studios and residences including Rocky Ranch, and of him and and Emma at the Crow Creek Reservation. Artwork is comprised of sketches Solon made for his sculptural works and for Sound Construction. Also found are sketches by Emma and Gutzon Borglum, including a sketch of Solon, and artwork by others such as artist Robert Fulton Logan.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 9 series. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1866, 1895-1922, undated (Box 1, 13; 10 folders)
Series 2: Family Correspondence, 1885-1972, undated (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 3: General Correspondence, 1871-1989, undated (Box 1-2; 1.0 linear foot)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, 1871-1983, undated (Box 2-3; 1.0 linear foot)
Series 5: Solon Borglum Biography, 1870-1975, undated (Box 3-8; 5.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Financial and Business Records, 1898-1998, undated (Box 8, 13; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1879-2002, undated (Box 9, 13-14; 1.1 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, 1864-1986 (Box 9-13, MGP 1, MGP 3, OV 15-16; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 9: Artwork, 1890-1921, undated (Box 12-13; 0.3 linear feet)
Provenance
Most of the materials in the collection were originally loaned by the Borglum family between 1969-1975 and microfilmed. Much of the same material was later donated in several accretions between circa 1991-2004 by various family members David Borglum, Harriet M. Borglum, Alfred Davies, Harold Davies, Monica B. Davies, Linda Borglum Fry, and Gwynneth Kelly. In 1979 approximately 200 photographs were transferred from the Smithsonian American Art Museum Library to AAA, which had received them from Monica Borglum Davies.
Separated Material
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm of material lent for microfilming (reels N69-98 and 1054) including a scrapbook of new clippings, other printed material, writings, and correspondence, much of which was included in subsequent donations. Loaned materials not donated at a later date are not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Related Material
The Archives also holds several collections related to the Borglum family, including the Gutzon Borglum collection, available on microfilm only, reel 3056. This collection includes correspondence, printed material, and photographs. Originals reside at the San Antonio Museum of Art. Also found are the Gutzon Borglum letters to John A. Stewart (available on microfilm reel D8, frames 359-362) and the Harriet Collins Allen papers relating to Solon Borglum. The Library of Congress also holds papers of Solon Hannibal Borglum and is the primary repository of the papers of Gutzon Borglum.
Alternative Forms Available
The papers of sculptor Solon Borglum and the Borglum Family were digitized in 2006 by the Archives of American Art, and total 6177 images.
Materials not digitized include a few certificates, writings and notes not authored by Solon but by others, Monica Borglum Davies research files for and drafts of the biography Solon H. Borglum, A Man Who Stands Alone, 1974, some routine financial materials, clippings and magazines, and photographs of artwork.
Materials lent for microfilming, most of which was later donated, merged, and digitized, are available on 35mm microfilm reels N69-98 and 1054 at Archives of American Art offices and for interlibrary loan.
Restrictions on Access
The bulk of the collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website. Use of material not digitized requires an appointment. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and not served to researchers.
Sculpture, American -- United States; Sculptors -- Connecticut -- Wilton; Sketches; Sculpture -- Study and teaching; World War, 1914-1918; Davies, Monica Borglum, 1903-1997; Davies, A. Mervyn (Alfred Mervyn); Borglum, Gutzon, 1867-1941; Borglum, Emma Vignal, 1864-1934
- Biographical Material, 1866, 1895-1922, undated; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 10 Folders Box 1, 13
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes citizenship papers for Solon's father, James Borglum, death certificates for two relatives, and other genealogical documents on the history of the Borglum Family. Also found are photographs, clippings, and other ephemera gathered in a leather portfolio by Emma Borglum. This series also contains items documenting Solon's role as Scoutmaster in Silvermine, as well as his service in World War I. Also found are written tributes and printed material for the Solon Borglum Memorials held at Saint Mark's in-the-Bouwerie and the National Sculpture Society. Folders are arranged chronologically by subject.
  - Declaration of Intention for Citizenship, James Borglum, 1866; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Death Certificates for Harry and Dagmar Wilson, 1895-1896; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Borglum Family History, 1896, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Emma Borglum Scrapbook/Porfolio, 1912; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Emma Borglum Scrapbook/Porfolio, 1912; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Emma Borglum Scrapbook/Porfolio, 1912; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Silvermine Boy Scout Troop, 1912, 1914; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Military Documents for Solon Borglum, 1917-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Scope and Contents
    Oversized material housed in Box 13, Folder 1
  - Solon Borglum Memorials, 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Military Documents for Solon Borglum, 1917-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 1, Folder 8
- Family Correspondence, 1885-1972, undated; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Family Correspondence includes numerous letters between Solon and his wife Emma and his children, Paul and Monica. Most of their correspondence is from 1918 through 1919 while Solon was in the military in France. There are also many letters to Monica from Emma during the period shortly after Solon's death. Also found are letters to Solon from his parents James and Ida; and letters to Emma from her parents Jean and Lydie Vignal. There are also many letters to Emma from her sister Lucy Vignal Borglum, who married Solon's brother August, and to Emma from her sister-in-law Elizabeth Vignal, who was married to Emma's brother Paul. Also included are numerous letters to Lucy Vignal Borglum from her parents. Most of the correspondence between the Vignals is in French. This series also contains other family correspondence including letters between Solon and his siblings, letters between Solon's brother August and other family members including several cousins, letters between Monica and Paul, Monica and her Aunt Harriet, and her cousin George Borglum, August Borglum's son. Much of this later correspondence discusses family history.
  - To wife Emma (and children) from Solon Borglum, 1907-1911; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - To wife Emma (and children) from Solon Borglum, 1918 January-June; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - To wife Emma (and children) from Solon Borglum, 1918 July-August; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - To wife Emma (and children) from Solon Borglum, 1918 August-October; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - To wife Emma (and children) from Solon Borglum, 1918 September-November; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - To wife Emma (and children) from Solon Borglum, November-December 1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - To wife Emma (and children) from Solon Borglum, 1919 January-April; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - To wife Emma (and children) from Solon Borglum, 1919 April-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - To Solon from wife Emma, 1901-1910; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - To Solon from wife Emma and Children, 1914-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - To Solon from wife Emma and Children, 1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - To Solon from wife Emma and Children, 1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - To Solon from parents James and Ida, 1897-1909, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - To Monica Borglum from her mother Emma, 1922-1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - To Monica Borglum from her mother Emma, 1923; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - To Monica Borglum from her mother Emma, 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - To Monica Borglum from her mother Emma, 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - To Emma from sister Lucy Vignal Borglum, 1903-1913, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - To Emma from sister-in-law Elizabeth Vignal, 1904-1923, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - To Emma from parents Jean and Lydie Vignal, 1902-1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - To Lucy Vignal Borglum from parents Jean and Lydie Vignal, 1902-1903; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - To Lucy Vignal Borglum from parents Jean and Lydie Vignal, 1903-1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - To Lucy Vignal Borglum from parents Jean and Lydie Vignal, 1905-1906; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - To Lucy Vignal Borglum from parents Jean and Lydie Vignal, 1907; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Family Correspondence, 1885-1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Family Correspondence, 1940-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Family Correspondence, 1955-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Family Correspondence, 1960-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Family Correspondence, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
- General Correspondence, 1871-1989, undated; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 1-2
  This series includes Solon Borglum's incoming and outgoing professional correspondence. Materials dated after 1922 are Monica Borglum Davies' incoming correspondence regarding Solon's artwork and legacy. Solon's correspondence is with galleries and foundries, such as the Milch Gallery and Roman Bronze Works, concerning the sale or production of his artwork, and correspondence with people and organizations, such as Jane Wallace and Saint Mark's in-the-Bouwerie, concerning sculpture projects, and with other artists, including August Saint-Gaudens and Robert Fulton Logan. Also found is correspondence concerning the School of American Sculpture, both before and after Solon's death.
  Materials addressed to Monica Borglum include letters from art galleries and museums, such as the Detroit Institute of Art, the Joslyn Art Museum, and the National Collection of Fine Arts at the Smithsonian Institution, concerning the sale or exhibition of Solon's artwork. Also included is correspondence with foundries concerning the production of Solon's sculptures, and with historical societies, individuals, and other organizations concerning the provenance, collection, or exhibition of his artwork. This series also includes correspondence from the Solon Borglum Memorial Fund and condolences to Monica on the deaths of Solon and Emma (in 1934).
  Also found are calling cards, business cards, and envelopes that have been separated from their contents. This series also includes numerous notepads containing drafts of Solon's outgoing correspondence as well as drafts on loose pages.
  - American Art Foundry, 1925-1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Collings, Ruth M., 1964-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Condolences, 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Condolences, 1922; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Condolences, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Condolences, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Cooper Hewitt Museum of Design, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Detroit Institute of Art, 1953-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Gallaher, E. B., 1924-1926, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - George F. Harding Museum, 1967-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Gorham Company, 1916-1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Grand Central Art Galleries, 1925-1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Hall, Wood, and Pound, 1908-1909; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Hugenot-Thomas Paine Historical Association, 1974-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Ingersoll, Raymond V., circa 1919, 1925-1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Joslyn Art Museum, 1958-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Knapp, Lamont P., 1950-1960, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Library of Congress, 1906, 1924, 1956, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Logan, Robert Fulton, 1920-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Massachusetts Monumental Company, 1909-1910; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Milch Galleries, 1920-1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - National Collection of Fine Arts, Smithsonian Institution, 1968-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - National Collection of Fine Arts, Smithsonian Institution, 1972-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Nebraska State Historical Society, 1965-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Perham, Douglas and Constance, 1959-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Randolph-Macon Women's College, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Requests for Copies of Sound Construction, 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Requests for Copies of Sound Construction, 1924-1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Roman Bronze Works, 1907-1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - School of American Sculpture, 1920-1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Saint-Gaudens, Augustus, 1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Saint Mark's In-The-Bouwerie (Dr. William Norman Guthrie), 1917-1925, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Solon Borglum Memorial Fund, 1922-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Tiffany and Co., 1911, 1925-1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Vogel, Emily (Mimi), 1964-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Wallace, Jane, 1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - General Correspondence, 1871-1907; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - General Correspondence, 1907-1908; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - General Correspondence, 1909; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1910; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1911; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1913-1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1920-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, 1924-1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, 1925-1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1953-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, 1965-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, 1973-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General Correspondence, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Calling Cards and Business Cards, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Envelopes, 1888, 1903-1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Loose Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Loose Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Notepads of Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, 1905-1910; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Notepads of Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, 1905-1910; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Notepads of Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, 1905-1910; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Notepads of Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, 1905-1910; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Notepads of Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Notepads of Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Notepads of Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Writings and Notes, 1871-1983, undated; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 2-3